A Guide to the Melita Rodeck Architectural Collection, 1931-2003, bulk 1960-1990
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Melita Rodeck Architectural Collection, 1931-2003, bulk, 1960-1990
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1992-028
10.7 cu. ft. 2 boxes; 30 oversize folders
The Melita Rodeck papers consist of architectural drawings designed by her while in private practice and as an employee of the U.S. federal government.
Rodeck, Melita
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Melita Rodeck Architectural Collection was donated to Special Collections in 1992, 1993, 1997, and 2003.
Biographical Information
Melita Rodeck was born on April 12, 1914, in Milan, Italy, to Austrian parents. After the outbreak of World War I her family returned to Vienna where she was educated. She enrolled at the Vienna Polytechnic in 1932 to study architecture, and immigrated to the United States in 1939. Upon arriving in the United States she spent four years volunteering in the Harlem slums. In 1950 she moved to Washington, D.C., and worked for the General Services Administration of the U.S. federal government. She became a registered architect of the District of Columbia in 1952 and established her own office in 1958, where she designed residences in Maryland and Virginia and restored townhouses in Washington, D.C.
From 1968 to 1973 Rodeck worked as an architect for special research projects at the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, then from 1973 to 1980 as a coordinator for architectural research for the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development. She was a program manager of Radiological Emergency Preparedness Programs for the Federal Emergency Management Agency from 1980 to 1985 and designed guidelines to minimize or eliminate flood damage to buildings. She retired from federal government work in 1985.
Rodeck was a devout Catholic and in the 1960s established the Regina Institute of Sacred Art, an organization dedicated to aiding Catholic parishes in their design and decoration efforts. The institute aimed to educate parishioners about the emotional impact of and psychological need for good design.
Scope and Content
The Melita Rodeck collection consists of architectural drawings designed by her while in private practice and as an employee of the U.S. federal government. The collection also includes various pieces of literature she wrote for the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers and the Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA).
Arrangement
The collection has been divided into four series: Personal Papers, Professional Papers, Project Records, and Artwork.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Architectural drawing--20th century.; International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA); Women-owned architectural firms.
Genre and Form Terms:
Architectural drawings.
Occupations:
Architects.
Contents List
- Personal Papers, 1960-2003
  - Clippings, 1960-2003
    - Rodeck,1964, 1984, 1987, 2003 (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Rodeck's Foggy Bottom residence,1960-1961, 1981,1991-1992, and undated (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Correspondence,1992, 1997, 2001, and undated (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Linoleum/woodcut prints by Rodeck (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Photographs of Rodeck (Box-folder 1:5)
  - School Work, 1933, 1971-1972
    - Drawing, Entwurf fur ein kinder walderholungsheim [possibly schoolwork due to the language] (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 8)
    - Presentation drawing, classical building, 1933 (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 3/Folder 2)
    - Neighborhood Commons Open Space [for Masters degree in City and Regional Planning],1971 (Box-folder 1:6)
    - Thesis: Flood Plain Management - A Search for a Unified Policy [for Masters degree in City and Regional Planning],December 1972 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Professional Papers, 1961-1984
  - Clippings,1961-1968
    - American Assocation of University Women (AAUW), 1967-1968 (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Melita Rodeck and Associates Architects and Engineers,1961 and undated (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Neighborhood Commons, 1963 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Curriculum Vitae,1968, 1982, and undated (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Publications,1968-1984
    - Space and Utilization Plans and Design Criteria for Army Guest House, Department of the Army, Office of the Chief of Engineers,1968 (Box-folder 1:12)
    - Construction--Space and Planning Criteria for U.S. Army Service Schools, Technical Manual, 5-843-1, for Department of the Army,1970. (Box-folder 1:13)
    - Interim Guidance for Two-Step Construction Contracting, Contracting Department, for the U.S. Army,1971. (Box-folder 1:14)
    - Historic Preservation--Booklet from the Office of the Chief of Engineers,1972. (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Elevated Residential Structures, FEMA publication,1976, 1984. (Box-folder 1:16)
    - Manual for the Construction of Residential Basements in Non-Coastal Flood Environs, HUD, Federal Insurance Adminstration publication,1978 (Box-folder 1:17)
    - Flood Emergency and Residential Repair Handbook, FEMA, 1979. (Box-folder 1:18)
    - Flood Plan Management Tools for Alluvial Fans, Study Plan, prepared for FEMA, 1980 (Box-folder 1:19)
    - Design Guidelines for Flood Damage Reduction, FEMA publication,1981. (Box-folder 1:20)
    - Flood Plan Management Tools for Alluvial Fans, Master Plan, prepared for FEMA,1981 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Regina Institute (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Writings, 1963-1969
    - Design and the Church, various articles,1963-1965 (Box-folder 1:23)
    - People's Space, American Association of University Women, 1969 (Box-folder 1:24)
- Project Records,1949-1975
  Arrangement
  The following is a list of Rodeck's projects from 1949-1975. It has been divided into five subseries: Church/Community Projects; Commercial/Residential Projects; Furniture/Miscellaneous; Government; and Urban Planning.
  Project/Client Name (location, date) [Format - Dr=Drawings, Ph=Photographs, Sp=Specifications, PB=Presentation Boards]
  - Church/Community Projects,1951-1968
    - Alter [Dr] (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Alter - walnut, [Dr] (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Archbishop's private chapel, [ Dr, PB] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 3/Folder 7, Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 2)
    - Aylesford Chapel, The National Scapular Center (Downers Grove, IL, 1959) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 2)
    - Banner of Resurrection, drawing [Dr] (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Blessed Martin Hospice Settlement House, conversion, 138 12th Street N.E. (1961) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 3)
    - Campus Chapel, University of Maryland, (College Park, MD) [Dr] (Box-folder 2:1)
    - Chapel of the White Fathers, renovation (Washington, D.C., 1967) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 3)
    - Church interior [ Dr ] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 4)
    - Church interior - JHS [ Dr ] (Oversize Oversize 15/Drawer 1/Folder 4)
    - Claretian Chapel, proposed modernization of chapel (1967-1968) [Dr] (Box-folder 1:25, Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 4)
    - Classroom module [ Dr ] (Box-folder 2:5)
    - Community Coffee House, St. Mary's Church, 730 23rd Street N.W. [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 3)
    - The Consolata Fathers, Missions Seminary, ( Buffalo, NY, 1958 ) [ Dr ] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 3)
    - Dunbarton College of the Holy Cross, proposed dormitory building (Washington, D.C.) [Dr] (Box-folder 2:1, Box-folder 2:3)
    - General Education Center [ Dr ] (Box-folder 2:3)
    - Gethsemani Infirmary ( 1952 ) [ Dr ] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 3)
    - Holy Comforter Church, proposed sanctuary remodeling (Charlottesville, VA, 1966) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 2)
    - Holy Rosary Church, alterations to meeting room, confessional (Washington, D.C., 1963 ) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 2)
    - Hospital chapel for 106 [ Dr ] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 4)
    - Immaculate Conception Chapel (Washington, D.C.) [Dr] (Box-folder 2:3, Box-folder 2:1)
    - Medical building, colored pencil exterior rendering [Dr] (Box-folder 2:3)
    - Neighborhood Commons (1964) [Dr, PB] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 1, Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 3/Folder 8)
    - Our Lady of Mt. Carmel, preliminary sketches for the shrine (Hamilton, MA, 1951) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 3)
    - Our Lady Star of the Sea, alterations (Indian Head, MD, 1960) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 3)
    - Parish Hall [ Dr ] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 4)
    - SS Paul and Augustine Commons (Washington, D.C., 1964) [Dr ] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 1)
    - St. Catherine's Church, landscaping (McConchie, MD, 1959) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 4)
    - St. Ignatius' Church, landscaping (Hilltop, MD, 1959) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 4)
    - St. Stephens Church/Parish Center, alterations (Washington, D.C., 1964-1966) [Dr, Sp] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 5, Box-folder 2:4, Box-folder 1:27)
    - St. Thomas Parish, listed as Regina Institute (Seattle, WA) [PB] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 3/Folder 8)
    - Youth Center, concept studies (1967) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 1)
  - Commercial/Residential Projects, 1949-1975
    - Abbot, Bernice, writing desk [Dr] (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Adler, John J., alterations to residence (Watertown, NY, 1949) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 4)
    - Apartment house, proposed alterations, 2110-19th Street N.W. (Washington, D.C., 1960) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 6)
    - Argus Builders, 9 unit apartment building, Atlantic Street, S.E. (Washington, D.C., 1966) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 9)
    - Calcara, Frank, store and apartment building (1967) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 2, Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 7)
    - Capitol Mansions, Inc., restoration of residence (Washington, D.C., 1965) [Dr, Ph] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 5, Box-folder 1:26)
    - Carbone, Donald, cottage, Chesapeake Ranch Club (1965) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 2)
    - Chilton Washington Corp., restoration of residence (Washington, D.C., 1965) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 5)
    - Clements, Everett, townhouses, Hughes Mews N.W. (Washington, D.C., 1963) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 1)
    - Clements, Everett, townhouses, 2513 Eye Street N.W. (Washington, D.C., 1963) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 1)
    - Coller, Harry, proposed store remodeling (Washington, D.C., 1966) [Dr ] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 6)
    - Co-Op apartments, proposed alterations to lodging house (Washington, D.C., 1961) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 1)
    - Crocker, John S., alteration and addition (Washington, D.C., 1965) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 2)
    - Efficiency units, 15 units, typical floor plan [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 6)
    - Engle, Morris, Harrigan's, proposed restaurant (1959) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 8)
    - Furth, Hans, alterations and additions (Washington, D.C., 1964) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 6)
    - Garner, Julian H., residence ( Washington, D.C., 1959) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 4)
    - Gross, William, living room [Dr] (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Gunston Library [PB] (Oversize Map-case 13/Drawer 3/Folder 9)
    - Harris, Forest K., flat conversion (Washington, D.C., 1963) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 5)
    - Heyn, Paul C., woodwork for living room (Hyattsville, MD, 1969) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 7)
    - Hotel Prince Frederick, (Prince Frederick, MD) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 3)
    - Jehle, Philip F.,addition to residence (Parkwood, Mont. Co., MD, 1962) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 9)
    - Jett, Page C., addition to residence (Prince Frederick, MD, 1965) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 7, Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 9)
    - Kaufman, Arthur, residence remodel (Washington, D.C., 1966) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 9)
    - Kirkwood Builders, apartment renovation (1965) [Dr, Ph] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 2, Box-folder 1:26)
    - Kraemer, Frank W., restoration and flat conversion (Washington, D.C., 1965) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 5)
    - Lee, M.B., reinforced concrete retaining wall (Washington, D.C., 1967) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 9)
    - Macgregor, Bruce, flat conversion (Washington, D.C., 1965) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 5)
    - May residence, proposed patio (Alexandria, VA, 1962) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 1)
    - McBride, Robert J., apartment house conversion (Washington, D.C., 1960) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 7, Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 4)
    - McBride, Robert J., alterations to residence ( Washington, D.C., 1960) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous interior/exterior renderings (11) [Dr] (Box-folder 2:6)
    - Miscellaneous residential renderings (2) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 6)
    - Mondlock, Marguerite, residence (Port Republic, MD, 1964) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 4)
    - Morris, Albert V., alterations to residence (1961) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 2)
    - Odarenko, T.M., alterations to residence (Washington, D.C., 1960) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 1)
    - Peon, N. Camara, residence (1960) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 10)
    - Professional Office Building, ( 1960) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 3)
    - Protos, Stephen D., reinforced concrete retaining wall (Silver Spring, MD, 1967) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 9)
    - Queen Anne's Lane Project, (Washington, D.C., 1960) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 7, Oversize Map-case 38/Drawer 8/Folder 4)
    - Reed, Sidney, residence [PB] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 3/Folder 1)
    - Rice, Josephine T., addition and remodeling (Washington, D.C., 1962) [Dr ] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 1)
    - Rodeck, Melita, residence, 801-25th Street N.W. (Washington, D.C., 1960) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 7)
    - Rodeck, Melita, flat conversion and addition, 2512 Eye Street N.W. (Washington, D.C., 1965, 1971) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 7)
    - Rodeck, Melita, proposed flat conversion, 2511 Eye St. N.W. (Washington, D.C., 1963) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 7)
    - Rodeck, Melita, alterations to flat, 213 10th Street S.E. (Washington, D.C., 1967) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 7)
    - Rodeck, Melita, Saltbox 3228, Monterey Place, lot 4 (1975) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 7)
    - Roumel, Aristotle and Theodore, residence (Washington, D.C., 1963) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 1)
    - Russin, Jonathan, restoration of residence (1966) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 2)
    - Seigel, Leonard M., proposed office building (Washington, D.C., 1965) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 8)
    - Singer, Louis, addition to residence (Washington, D.C., 1965) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 6)
    - Smith, William J., residence remodel (1962) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 1)
    - Thorman, Burton, addition to residence (Arlington, VA, 1961) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 10)
    - Thornton, Ruth E., restoration of residence (Washington, D.C., 1964) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 10)
    - Van der Reyden, apartment (Washington, D.C., 1958-1959) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 10)
    - Van Mater, B., addition to residence (1961) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 2)
    - VIP Lounge, [PB] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 3/Folder 9)
    - Wallace, Mary, residence (Dare's Beach, MD, 1958) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 1)
    - Wallins, Sam, proposed auto repair shop (Watertown, NY, 1966) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 8)
    - Watters, James, remodeling of residence (1961) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 10)
    - Weinberg, Milton, 6 unit apartment building, 2913 30th Street SE ( 1966) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 7, Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 6)
    - Weinberg, Milton, 6 unit apartment building, 4016 Livingston Road, S.E. (1966) [Dr, PB] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 6, Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 3/Folder 1, Box-folder 1:25)
    - Weinberg, Milton, 12 unit apartment building, 117 Atlantic Street SE (1966) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 6, Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 7)
    - Yahraes, Marjorie, addition to residence (Washington, D.C., 1962) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 1)
    - Yeager, Inez, residence (Accokeek, MD, 1959 ) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 10)
    - Zeiger, Leon, draughter's bedroom (1967) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 2)
    - Ziglar, Robert, addition to residence (1968) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 10)
  - Furniture/Miscellaneous, 1966 and undated
    - Duckboard, 6'x10' (1966) [Dr] (Box-folder 2:6)
    - Sofa, walnut or teak [Dr] (Box-folder 2:6)
    - Tea cart, walnut [Dr] (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Government, 1953-1966
    - Andrews Air Force Base, traffic check house (Washington, D.C., 1959) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 8/Folder 1)
    - Andrews Air Force Base, alterations to Air Com facility, building 1558 (Washington, D.C., 1962 ) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 8/Folder 1)
    - Andrews Air Force Base, Hanger and Shops, Boiler House (MD, 1955) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 8/Folder 1)
    - Andrews Air Force Base, modification of Hanger, building 1-180 (Washington, D.C., 1959) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 8/Folder 1)
    - Barracks [Dr] (Box-folder 2:5)
    - District Training School. Department of Welfare, Holly Cottage, Dogwood Cottage (mechanical and electrical drawings) (Laural, MD) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 8/Folder 3)
    - District Training School. Department of Welfare, renovation of basements om Pine, Oak, and Maple Cottages (Laural, MD, 1966) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 8/Folder 3)
    - Federal Records Center, replace roof (Alexandria, VA, 1953) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 8/Folder 2)
    - Guest house concept study [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 7)
    - Health, Education and Welfare, South Building, dental clinic renovation (Washington, D.C., 1953) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 8/Folder 2, Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 8)
    - Office of the Post Engineer, rehabilitation of Mess Hall, building 18 (Fort Belvoir, VA, 1957) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 8/Folder 2)
    - U.S. Naval Radio Research Station, annex building for 60 foot antenna (Sugar Grove, WV, 1961) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 8/Folder 2)
    - U.S. Naval Research Laboratory--Stairway and Hallway Fire Protection, various buildings. plans for buildings 1, 12, 13, 30 (1959) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 35/Drawer 8/Folder 2)
    - Unit Entertainment Center [Dr] (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Urban Planning, 1960, 1975, and undated
    - Air rights development in Foggy Bottom, architectural drawing (Washington, D.C., 1975), [Dr] (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Foggy Bottom Park [Dr, PB] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 3/Folder 1, Box-folder 2:4, Box-folder 2:3)
    - Elevated In-Town Heliport (1960) [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 3)
    - High rise city for two hundred thousand, design concept [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 2/Folder 3)
    - Ideal Neighborhood [PB] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 3/Folder 1)
    - Potomac Plaza, proposed [Dr] (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 1/Folder 1)
- Artwork, 1931 and undated
  - Abstract prints, metallic (3) (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 3/Folder 4)
  - Charcoal, portraits (2) (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 3/Folder 2)
  - Pencil, Vienna, 1931 (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 3/Folder 5)
  - Sketchbooks (2) (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 3/Folder 3)
  - Various mediums (4) (Oversize Map-case 15/Drawer 3/Folder 6)